(pg.168) JM: then that bird looked back
JP: alta uk kəlákəlá yaka nanich-k'ilapay
JM: and he saw that in place of the boy there were only bones
JP: alta yaka nanich-k'ilapay uk tənas-man
JM: they continued to go down the river (and Blue-Jay was quiet)
JP: yaka ɬatwa alta yawa kʰupa ukuk hayas chək... ukuk kəlákələ hilu ikta yaka wawa
JM: he looked back and the boy was sitting there again
JP: yaka nanich k'ilapay yawa tənəs-man yaka miɬayt wəx̣t kʰupá
JM: he said to him in a low voice
JP: yaka wawa kʰupa yaka tənas-man
JM: what is....where is your weir
JP: qʰa ukuk alta > k'ilapay
JM: he spoke slowly
JP: yaka wawa tunús wawa
JM: the boy replied
JP: ukuk tənas-man yaka wawa
JM: it is down the river
JP: yawa saya kikwəli kʰupa-ukuk chək
JM: they went on
JP: ɬaska ɬatwa yawa
JM: then he said to him in a loud voice
JP: alta yaka wawa kʰupa yaka hayash wawa
JM: where is your weir
JP: qʰa alta yax̣ka
JM: and only a skeleton was there (in the stern of the canoe)
JP: kʰəpit-ukuk ayaq tilay-miməlust alta kʰupá
JM: the bird was silent again
JP: ukuk kəlákəlá yaka hayaʔ... hilu-wawa wəx̣t
JM: he looked back and the boy was there again
JP: yaka nanich-k'ilapay pi uk tənəs-man wəx̣t yaka kʰupá
JM: then he said in a low voice
JP: yaka wawa kʰupa tənəs-wawa
JM: where is your weir
JP: qʰa ukuk alta >
JM: "here" says the boy
JP: yakwa yaka wawa tənəs-man
JM: now they fished with their dipnets
JP: alta ɬaska > alta ɬaska mamuk samən >  ɬaska dipnet
JM: the bird felt something in his net
JP: alta tənəs-man yaka ih...iskam ikta kʰupa yaka net
JM: he lifted it
JP: yaka mamuk ɬax̣
JM: and he found only two branches in his net
JP: yaka t'ɬap kʰopit ixt tənəs lima-stik kʰupa yaka net
JM: he turned his net and threw it into the water
JP: yaka mash yaka net wəx̣t kʰupa chək
JM: it became full of leaves
JP: yaka chaku-pʰaɬ ukuk kʰanawi
JM: he turned his net and threw them into the water
JP: yaka mamuk-k'ilapay yaka net pi yaka mash wəx̣t kʰupa chək
JM: but part of the leaves fell into the canoe
JP: bət > nawitka kʰupá kənim
JM: the boy gathered them up
JP: ukuk tənəs-man yaka iskam kʰanawi
JM: then another branch came into the bird's net
JP: alta wəx̣t uk ɬatwa t'ɬux̣ kʰupa ukuk yaka net
JM: he turned the net and threw it into the water
JP: yaka mamuk-k'ilapay ukuk pi yaka mash kʰupa chək
JM: some leaves came into it and he threw it into the water
JP: > ukuk chaku wəx̣t kʰupa ukuk > pi yaka mash ɬaska kʰupa chək
JM: all of the leaves fell into the canoe
JP: > yaka t'ɬux̣ kʰupá ukuk kənim
JM: the boy gathered them up
JP: ukuk tənəs-man yaka iskam ukuk kʰanawi
JM: the bird was pleased with two of the branches
JP: ukuk tənəs-man yaka ɬush-təmtəm yaka makwst tənəs lima-stik
JM: "I will carry them home" he said
JP: > ɬaska nayka > kʰupa > haws
JM: she may use them for making fire
JP: alax̣ti yaka mamuk paya ɬaska ukuk
JM: these branches branches were large
JP: wəx̣t alta yaka təmtəm lima-stik ɬaska ɬush
JM: they arrived at home and went up to the house
JP: yaka iskam wəx̣t > yaka ɬatwa kʰupa yaka haws
JM: the bird was angry
JP: ukuk tənəs-man ukuk kəlákəlá tənəs-saliks
JM: because he had not caught anything
JP: because he... pus hilu-ikta yaka iskam
JM: they boy brought a mat full of trout up to the house
JP: uk tənəs-man yaka mamuk-k'ilapay pʰaɬ ɬiskwis kʰupa yaka haws
JM: and the people roasted them
JP: ukuk tilixam ɬaska paya ɬaska ukuk > paya-stik
JM: then the boy told them
JP: ukuk tənəs.. ukuk tənəs-man yaka wawa kʰupa yaka
JM: he threw out of the canoe what we had caught
JP: ikta mayka mash kʰupa ukuk kənim ɬax̣ani yaka iskam
JM: our canoe would have been full if he had not thrown it away
JP: ukuk kənim yaka pʰaɬ pus wik yaka mash ɬax̣ani
JM: his sister said to him
JP: pi yaka ats yaka wawa kʰupa yax̣ka
JM: why did you throw away what you had caught?
JP: qʰata > mayka mash ukuk ikta mayka iskam
JM: I threw it away because we had caught nothing but branches
JP: nayka mash ukuk pus hilu-ikta mamuk iskam.  kʰəpit ukuk lima-stik.
JM: "that is our food" she said
JP: kʰupá ukuk nsayka məkmək
JM: do you think they were leaves?
JP: nayka munk-təmtəm kʰəltəs-ikta ukuk
JM: those leaves were trout
JP: ukuk...ukuk ikta yaka tənəs-samən
JM: the branches salmon
JP: ukuk tənəs lima-stik yaka samən
JM: he said to his sister
JP: yaka wawa kʰupa yaka ats
JM: I brought you two branches
JP: nayka lulú kʰupa ma..mayka makwst lima-stik
JM: you may use them for making fire
JP: mayka mamuk paya kʰupa ukuk
JM: then his sister went down to the beach
JP: alta yaka ats yaka ɬatwa yawa kʰupa ukuk tən-chək
JM: now there were two salmon in the canoe
JP: alta kʰupá makwst samən ukuk kənim.. kʰupa ukuk kənim
JM: she carried them up to the house
JP: alta yaka lulu kʰupa ukuk kʰupa haws
JM: and she enters carrying them in her hands
JP: yaka q'uʔ yaka ɬatwa haws ukuk yaka mamuk-k'ilapay kʰupa yaka lima
JM: then the bird said
JP: alta kəlákələ yaka wawa
JM: where did you steal these salmon?
JP: kʰupa qʰa mayka iskam ukuk samən kapshwala
JM: "that is what you caught" she said
JP: ukuk ikta mayka iskam
JM: my sister is lying
JP: nayka ats yaka t'ɬəminxwət kʰupa mayka
JM: on the next day the bird went to the beach
JP: iwa wəx̣t san ukuk kəlákəlá yaka ɬatwa  kʰupa chək
JM: there lay the canoe of the ghosts
JP: qʰa uk kʰupá yaka miɬayt ukuk kənim ukuk > miməlust tilixam yaka kənim
JM: they had all holes and part of them were mossgrown
JP: kənim ɬaska mmm..hilu... pʰaɬ-ɬxwap ɬq'up-ɬq'up. ɬaska miɬayt ukuk hayu-ikta yaka chaku-hayash kʰupá
JM: he went to the house and said to his sister
JP: yaka ɬatwa yawa kʰupa haws. yaka wawa kʰupa yaka ats
JM: your husband's canoes are bad
JP: ukuk mayka (cough)...ukuk mayka man yaka kənim...mashachi alta
JM: "be quiet" she said
JP: nayka uk nayka wik-ikta wawa yaka wawa
JM: the people will become tired of you
JP: ukuk tilixam ɬaska mitxwit chaku tʰil kʰupa mayka
JM: the canoes of these people are full of holes
JP: wəx̣t ukuk kənim ukuk tilixam ɬq'up-pʰaɬ ɬxwap
JM: then his sister said to him
JP: alta yaka ats yaka wawa kʰupa yaka
JM: are they people?
JP: yaka m... ɬaska tili...tilixam....kʰanawi?
JM: they are ghosts
JP: alta kʰupa miməlust tilixam ukuk bons ɬaska
JM: it grew dark again
JP: alta yaka chaku pulakʰli
JM: and the bird made himself ready
JP: alta uk kəlákəlá yaka mamuk-ɬush
JM: and the boy made himself ready also
JP: alta tənas man yaka mamuk ɬush wəx̣t
JM: they went again
JP: alta wəx̣t ɬaska ɬatwa
JM: now he sees the boy
JP: alta yaka nanich ukuk tənas-man
JM: when they were on their way he shouted
JP: yaka ɬatwa kʰəltəs-saya ɬaska p'uʔ yaka
JM: and only bones were there
JP: kʰəpit ukuk yaka bons  kʰupá
JM: he did this several times before he arrived
JP: yaka mamuk alta qʰənchi-hayu... > k'ilapay... q'u kʰupá
JM: now they fished with a dipnet
JP: alta ɬaska miɬayt  > ɬaska mamuk samən ukuk ɬaska dipnet
JM: he gathered the branches and the leaves which he had caught
JP: alta ɬaska iskam ukuk kʰanawi > ɬaska iskam lima-stik kʰanawi-ikta
JM: > in their canoe was full
JP: qʰənchi ukuk hayash chək chaku-k'ilapay ɬaska > kənim pʰatɬ alta
JM: then they went home
JP: alta ɬaska k'ilapay kʰupa ɬaska haws
JM: now he sees the door
JP: alta yaka nanich.. ukuk...> alta miməlust tilixam ya kənim
JM: he shouted as soon as they met one
JP: ɬaska yaka kʰriye > ɬaska nanich ixt
JM: and only bones could be seen
JP: kʰəpit ukuk yaka bons ɬaska nanich
JM: they arrived at home
JP: ɬaska q'uʔ kʰupa yaka haws
JM: he went up to his sister
JP: yaka ɬatwa kʰupa yaka ats
JM: he carried up the salmon which he had caught
JP: yaka mamuk-q'uʔ yakwa uk samən ɬaska iskam mamuk-chaku
JM: the next morning
JP: >
JM: the bird went into the town
JP: ukuk kəlákələ yaka ɬatwa yawa kʰupa tʰawn
JM: he found many bones in the house
JP: yaka t'ɬap hayu bon kʰupa yaka haws
JM: when it grew dark, somebody said
JP: yaka chaku pulakʰli, ɬaksta yaka wawa
JM: a whale has been found
JP: ukuk hayash samən ɬaska iskam
JM: his sister gave him a knife and said to him
JP: ukuk yaka ats palach yaka uptsax̣ > yaka wawa kʰupa yax̣ka
JM: run, a whale has been found
JP: kuri...kuri-ayaq, > hayash samən ɬaska iskam
JM: the bird ran and came to the beach
JP: ukuk kəlakəla yaka ɬax̣...kuli yawa kʰupa > saya kʰupa hayash-chək
JM: he met one of the people
JP: yaka ɬatwa >>..ixt tilixam
JM: speaking loudly he asked
JP: yaka wawa
JM: where is that whale?
JP: ikta... qʰa ukuk hayash samən?
JM: only a skeleton layed there
JP: kʰəpit ukuk bon yaka miɬayt kʰupá
JM: he kicked the skull and left it
JP: yaka iskam ukuk yaka... miməlust yaka latet yaka >
JM: he went some distance and met other people
JP: yaka kuri ukuk tənəs-saya pi yaka ɬatwa x̣luyma tilixam
JM: he shouted loudly
JP: yaka kʰriye tənəs-hayash
JM: only skeletons lay there
JP: kʰəpit ukuk yaka bon-miməlust-tilixam miɬayt kʰupá
JM: several times he acted this way towards the people
JP: qʰənchi yaka hayu-mamuk kakwa > kʰupá
JM: then he came to a large log
JP: > mamuk  kʰupá ukuk hayash stik >
JM: it's bark was very thick
JP: ukuk...> yaka skin dret hayash
JM: there was a crowd of people who peeled off the bark
JP: hayu tilixam ɬaska munk-ɬaq-ɬaq ukuk yaka skin
JM: the bird shouted
JP: ukuk kəlákələ yaka kʰriye
JM: only skeletons lay there
JP: kʰəpit ukuk yaka bon miməlust-tilixam miɬayt kʰupá
JM: the bark was full of pitch
JP: ukuk...ukuk uhh...hayash stik yaka skin kʰupit-kʰanawi > pʰatɬ-lakum
JM: he peeled off two pieces
JP: yaka mamuk-ɬaq makwst
JM: he carried them on his shoulder and went home
JP: yaka lulu ɬas kʰupa yaka shoulder yaka lulu hom, yaka lulu kʰupa yaka haws
JM: he thought
JP: yaka təmtəm
JM: I really believed it is a whale
JP: nayka  dilet kəmtəks ya təmtəm alta ya wawa uk hayash samən miɬayt
JM: when he arrived he put down the bark outside the house
JP: yaka q'uʔ kʰupa yaka haws yaka mash ukuk yaka skin ya... stik-skin yawa ɬax̣ani
JM: he said to his sister
JP: yaka wawa kʰupa yaka ats
JM: I thought it was a whale
JP: nayka təmtəm ukuk yaka hayash samən
JM: look here it is bark
JP: nanich ukuk > lakum-stik yaka skin
JM: it is whale meat
JP: yax̣ka ukuk hayash samən yaka iɬwəli
JM: do you think it is bark?
JP: mayka mamuk-təmtəm ukuk yaka stik-skin
JM: his sister went out and two cuts of whale lay on the ground
JP: yaka... yaka ats yaka ɬatwa ɬax̣ani yaka nanich ukuk makwst  kʰupa hayash samən yaka  yawa
JM: it is a good whale
JP: yaka hayash ɬush ukuk hayash samən yakwa
JM: it is very thick
JP: hayash hayash
JM: then the bird looked and there lay a whale on the beach
JP: alta yaka nanich ukuk kəlákələ yaka nanich hayash samən yawa miɬayt
JM: he turned back
JP: yaka k'ilapay
JM: he met a person carrying bark on his back
JP: yaka  nanich uk tilixam lulu skin-stik kʰupa  shoulder yawa
JM: he shouted and nothing but a skeleton lay there
JP: yaka kʰriye  hilu-ikta kʰupit  miməlust-tilixam yaka bons kʰupá
JM: he took that piece of bark and carried it home on his shoulder
JP: yaka lulu-iskam ukuk wəx̣t ɬq'up-skin-stik yaka lulu kʰupa yaka haws
JM: this he did to all of the ghosts
JP: kakwa yaka mamuk > ukuk > miməlust-tilixam yaka lulu ɬatwa kʰupá
JM: in the course of time he had much whale meat
JP:  kənim hayu kʰupit-ixt yax̣ka yaka iskam ukuk  >>
JM: now he continued to stay there
JP: alta yaka miɬayt kʰupá kwansəm
JM: he went again to that town
JP: alta wəx̣t yaka ɬatwa ukuk hayash tʰawn.. o...hayu haws
JM: he entered a house and took this child's skull
JP: yaka iskam kʰupa ixt... ɬatwa kʰupa ixt haws, yawa yaka iskam ukuk tənas yaka latet
JM: which he put on a large skeleton
JP: yaka mamuk miɬayt kʰupa hayash bons... mimelust tilixam yaka bons
JM: he took a large skull and he put on a child's skeleton
JP: yaka iskam hayash tilixam yaka latet pi  latet
JM: this he did to all the people
JP: kakwa yaka mamuk > kʰanawi ukuk tilixam
JM: when it grew dark the child rose to speak
JP: qʰənchi yaka chaku pulakʰli ukuk tənas yaka mash kʰupa-ukuk hayu-wawa
JM: it wanted to sit up
JP: yaka tiki miɬayt
JM: so it fell down again because it's head pulled it down
JP: yaka t'ɬux̣ wəx̣t ukuk pus yaka latit mamuk-hal yax̣ka ikta
JM: the old man rose
JP: ukuk ulman yaka miɬayt
JM: his head was light
JP: yaka latit
JM: the next morning they replaced the head
JP:  tənəs san -miɬayt k'ilapay uk latet
JM: sometimes he did this to the legs of the ghost
JP: kakupus  kakupus yaka mamuk  miməlust tilixam kwansəm
JM: he gave small legs to  people
JP: yaka paɬlach...yaka paɬlach ukuk hayash lipʰyi kʰupa hayash tilixam
JM: and large legs to a small child
JP: pi hayu hayash lipʰyi kʰupa
JM: sometimes he exchanged a man's and a woman's legs
JP: ixt-ixt pus yaka mamuk... mamuk x̣luyma ukuk ɬuchmən yaka lipʰyi
JM: in the course of time they began to dislike him
JP: ukuk alta tənəs yax̣ka tənəs-lili alta uk tilixam wik-tiki yax̣ka
JM: tell him he shall go home they said
JP: alta ɬaska wawa ɬuchmən ya ɬatwa-haws alta
JM: that is what his brother-in-law said to his sister
JP:
JM: on the next morning he awoke early
JP:  tənəs-san .... ....mayka miɬayt tənəs-san
JM: now his sister held a skull in her arms
JP: alta ukuk yaka ats yaka
JM: he threw it away
JP: yaka mash yawa
JM: why did you hold that old skull again
JP: qʰata  mayka iskam ukuk miməlust tilixam yaka latet
JM: you broke your brother-in-law's neck
JP: mayka mamuk  ukuk mayka aw yaka liku
JM: it grew dark
JP: yaka chaku pulakʰli
JM: now his brother-in-law was sick
JP: alta yaka aw yaka hayash sik
JM: the wom...the man tried to cure himself
JP: kakupus ixt man yaka tiki mamuk ɬush yaka
JM: he became alive again
JP: yaka chaku ɬush
JM: now the boy went home
JP: alta ukuk kəlákəlá yaka ɬatwa kʰupa yaka haws
JM: his sister gave him five buckets full of water
JP: yaka ats paɬlach yaka kitɬən, qwinəm ukuk, chək...hmm chək
JM: and he told him
JP: wawa kʰupa yax̣ka
JM: take care
JP: mayka ɬush-nanich
JM: when you come to the burning prairies
JP: mayka chaku kʰupa ukuk, alta, ukuk paya ɬush-iliʔi
JM: do not pour it out til you come to the fourth prairie
JP: mayka mamuk-wax̣ pus mayka chaku ukuk (on) paya... ɬush-iliʔi
JM: then pour it out
JP: alta mayka mash ukuk mayka chək kʰupá
JM: now he went
JP: alta yaka ɬatwa
JM: he reached the prairie
JP: yaka q'uʔ kʰupa ukuk hayash ɬush-iliʔi
JM: it was hot
JP: hayash wam yaka kʰupá
JM: red flowers bloomed on the prairie
JP:  ukuk ukuk ukuk pʰil t'səm > chaku kʰupá
JM: they poured water on
JP: yaka mamuk-wax̣... yaka mamuk-wax̣ kʰupa ukuk chək kʰupá
JM: one of his buckets was half empty
JP: ukuk kit... ukuk ixt yaka kitɬən wik...wik saya...katsaq
JM: he leaves the woods
JP: yaka  kʰupa ukuk stik >
JM: and soon he came to another prairie
JP: wik lili wəx̣t yaka chaku kʰapuk tənəs-ɬush-iliʔi
JM: which was burning at it's end
JP: yaka wəx̣t kʰupa ukuk hayash paya kʰupá
JM: he reached another prairie which was half on fire
JP: pi wəx̣t q'uʔ  kʰupa ixt tənəs-ɬush-iliʔi wəx̣t kʰupa paya